<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2006"><identification id="aces" isproject="true"><shortname><span class="smallcap" align="left">aces</span></shortname><projectName>Ambient Computing and Embedded Systems</projectName><theme>COM</theme><team id="uid1"><participants category="Head_of_project-team"><person><firstname>Michel</firstname><lastname>Banâtre</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro><moreinfo>Research Director, INRIA</moreinfo><hdr>oui</hdr></person></participants><participants category="Administrative_assistant"><person><firstname>Evelyne</firstname><lastname>Livache</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro></person></participants><participants category="INRIA_project_staff"><person><firstname>Ciaran</firstname><lastname>Bryce</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro><moreinfo>Research Director, INRIA</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Paul</firstname><lastname>Couderc</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro><moreinfo>Research Scientist, INRIA</moreinfo></person></participants><participants category="CNRS_project_staff"><person><firstname>Jean-Paul</firstname><lastname>Routeau</lastname><affiliation>CNRS</affiliation><categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro><moreinfo>Senior technical staff, CNRS</moreinfo></person></participants><participants category="University_project_staff"><person><firstname>Frédéric</firstname><lastname>Weis</lastname><affiliation>UnivFr</affiliation><categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro><moreinfo>Assistant Professor, IUT de Saint-Malo</moreinfo></person></participants><participants category="Project_technical_staff"><person><firstname>Fabien</firstname><lastname>Allard</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro></person><person><firstname>Mathieu</firstname><lastname>Becus</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro></person><person><firstname>Ronan</firstname><lastname>Menard</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro><moreinfo>since 1/2/2006</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Antoine</firstname><lastname>Luu</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro><moreinfo>up to 31/8/2006</moreinfo></person></participants><participants category="Ph._D._student"><person><firstname>Damien</firstname><lastname>Martin-Gutteriez</lastname><affiliation>UnivFr</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>ENS grant</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Mickaël</firstname><lastname>LeBaillif</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>Inria grant</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Xavier</firstname><lastname>Le Bourdon</lastname><affiliation>UnivFr</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>MESR grant</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Pierre</firstname><lastname>Duquesne</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>INRIA grant, since 1/10/2006</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Azza</firstname><lastname>Jediddi</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>INRIA grant, since 1/10/2006</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Claude</firstname><lastname>Vittoria</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>Inria grant</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Cedric</firstname><lastname>Mosch</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>Inria grant</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Arnaud</firstname><lastname>Guiton</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>Inria grant</moreinfo></person><person><firstname>Mazen</firstname><lastname>Tlais</lastname><affiliation>INRIA</affiliation><categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro><moreinfo>Inria grant</moreinfo></person></participants></team><UR name="Rennes"/></identification><presentation id="uid3"><bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid4"><bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle><p>Three key phenomena have been changing the nature of computing over the last few years. The first is the popularity of portable devices such as mobile telephones and Personal Digital Assistants (PDAs). Today, around 80%
of the French adult population possess their own mobile phone and there is a large variety of smartphones on the market that integrate PDA functionality. The second phenomenon is the large number of embedded systems; these are everyday devices that have their own processor and memory. Estimates suggest that more than 98%
of the world's processor's are in embedded systems <ref xlink:href="#bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>, thus facilitating the deployment of a variety of information systems that control physical objects. The third phenomena is the increasing variety of wireless networks available for personal and embedded devices, e.g., Bluetooth, Wifi, GPRS, etc.</p><p>The combination of these three phenomena has permitted the emergence of context-aware person-centric applications and services. These services complement a person's physical ability to interact with his environment. They are tailored to a the needs, preferences and location of each person carrying a device, and are continually available. Services range from critical, e.g., remote health monitoring <ref xlink:href="#bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>, to utility, e.g., navigational help, etc. to value-added, e.g., virtual museum guides, smart home, etc.</p><p>The domain of person-centric computing is known in research circles as <i>ambient computing</i> <ref xlink:href="#bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>, and several significant research challenges remain. First, to facilitate mobility, ambient computing services should require minimal device manipulation by the device owner. It is crucial that the computing device operate as an extension of the person rather than as a tool. Second, there must be a way of modeling the physical environment so that applications can seamlessly import data from the environment and modify the environment when possible. Third, applications must be able to adapt to the rather limited storage and processing capabilities of mobile devices, as well as to variable and intermittent wireless network coverage.</p><p>The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Aces</span> (Ambient Computing and Embedded Systems) group is addressing research from three angles<footnote id="uid5" place="foot" anchored="yes">At the outset of the four-year period, we also had real-time system support as an objective. However, this research theme ended when Isabelle Puaut left the group in 2004.</footnote>:</p><simplelist><li id="uid6"><p><i>Programming Models for Ambient Computing</i>. We have looked at ways of modeling the physical environment in the virtual environment of programs in order to facilitate ambient application development. The goal is to be able to write programs that address and navigate through objects in the physical world as elegantly as a program traditionally manipulates a computer's main memory.</p></li><li id="uid7"><p><i>Quality of Ambient Service</i>. A user needs to be able to exploit ambient services as seamlessly as possible. In particular, he should be shielded from the effects of network breaks – something that can be quite common for wireless environments. We have been developing for ensuring continuous video streaming for mobile devices.</p></li><li id="uid8"><p><i>Operating System Support</i>. We are looking at portable operating system designs for personal devices that manage limited physical resources and irregular network connectivity.</p></li></simplelist><p>Throughout 2006, in accordance with the goals of the institute, the ACES group spent a great deal of time and effort
on seeking to transfer its research results on ambient computing to potential users. We sought out and negotiated
with representatives of end-users in advertising and the urban construction industries.
Our motivation stems from our observation that producing innovative research results, even those protected by patents,
is no longer sufficient for a modern research team. It is essential to convince industry that solutions are robust,
scalable and most importantly, address a problem that real users are faced with. This research approach
necessitates the development of several prototypes that are tested in real environments. It also necessitates
a continuous technology watch to ensure the validity of submitted patents, as well as verification of existing
patents and research reports. Although this activity is, traditionally, unusual for a research team, it becomes inevitable
if results are to have a real impact in the ambient computing applications currently being deployed.</p><p>Our technology transfer efforts have been very successful. A start-up company called UbiSphere went into INRIA incubator status in
October 2006. A major patent was transferred to JCDecaux – the worldwide billboard operator – in February 2006. From November 2006 to February 2007, the group has been commissioned by ADP to design and implement a pilot of an ambient system, based on the group's technology, for use in airport environments.</p><p>Despite our work with industrial partners, we have not neglected academic partners. For instance, we are participating in Mosaic – a research project financed by the French government. At a European level, we are participating in the Resist network of Excellence, the Wisents coordinated action and, since November 2006, the Roboswarm EU project.</p><p>This document overviews our activities in more detail. The section
<i>Scientific Foundations</i> gives some background to our work in
person-centric computing. The section <i>Application Domains</i> describes the
importance of our research agenda through the presentation of several
applications, some of which are being developed in our group. The group's
recent results are presented in the section <i>New Results</i>.</p></subsection></presentation><fondements id="uid9"><bodyTitle>Scientific Foundations</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid10"><bodyTitle>Introduction</bodyTitle><keyword>Embedded systems</keyword><keyword>hard/soft real-time</keyword><keyword>energy
consumption</keyword><keyword>design tools</keyword><keyword>ubiquitous computing</keyword><keyword>ambient
computing</keyword><keyword>spatial navigation</keyword><p>The following paragraphs give a quick overview of the scientific
background of the ACES research activities.
Ambient computing and embedded systems are the foundations of person-centric
computing. Our group is concentrating on <i>programming models</i> and
<i>operating system support</i>; these are two essential and complementary
aspects of ambient computing.</p><p>The purpose of a programming model is to represent information as data, and to
provide a computational framework for data processing. The challenge for
ambient and embedded computing is to seamlessly merge information from the
physical and virtual worlds, so that programs can act upon and influence the
physical world around them.</p><p>The goal of our research on operating system support is to define platforms
that enable programs to run on resource-limited devices, where wireless
network connection fluctuates. In particular, we are looking at environments
built around Java<span class="math" align="left"><sup><hi rend="it">T</hi><hi rend="it">M</hi></sup></span> technology, in order to maximise application safety
and portability.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid11"><bodyTitle>Programming Models</bodyTitle><p>The goal of ambient computing is to seamlessly merge virtual and real
environments. A real environment is composed of objects from the physical
world, e.g., people, places, machines. A virtual environment is any
information system, e.g., the Web. The integration of these environments must
permit people and their information systems to implicitly interact with their
surrounding environment.</p><p>Ambient computing applications are able to evaluate the state of the real
world through sensing technologies. This information can include the position
of a person (caught with a localisation system like GPS), the weather
(captured using specialised sensors), etc. Sensing technologies enable
applications to automatically update digital information about events or
entities in the physical world. Further, interfaces can be used to act on the
physical world based on information processed in the digital environment. For
example, the windows of a car can be automatically closed when it is raining.</p><p>This real-world and virtual-world integration must permit people to implicitly
interact with their surrounding environment. This means that manual device
manipulation must be minimal since this constrains person mobility. In any
case, the relative small size of personal devices can make them awkward to
manipulate. In the near future, interaction must be possible without people
being aware of the presence of neighbouring processors.</p><subsection id="uid12"><bodyTitle>Programming Context</bodyTitle><p>Information systems require tools to <i>capture</i> data in its physical
environment, and then to <i>interpret</i>, or process, this data. A context
denotes all information that is pertinent to a person-centric application.
There are three classes of context information:</p><simplelist><li id="uid13"><p>The <i>digital context</i> defines all parameters related to the
hardware and software configuration of the device. Examples include the
presence (or absence) of a network, the available bandwidth, the connected
peripherals (printer, screen), storage capacity, CPU power, available
executables, etc.</p></li><li id="uid14"><p>The <i>personal context</i> defines all parameters related to the
identity, preferences and location of the person who owns the device. This
context is important for deciding the type of information that a personal
device needs to acquire at any given moment.</p></li><li id="uid15"><p>The <i>physical context</i> relates to the person's environment; this
includes climatic condition, noise level, luminosity, as well as date and
time.</p></li></simplelist><p>All three forms of context are fundamental to person-centric computing.
Consider for instance a virtual museum guide service that is offered via a
PDA. Each visitor has his own PDA that permits him to receive and visualise
information about surrounding artworks. In this application, the
<i>pertinent</i> context of the person is made up of the artworks situated
near the person, the artworks that interest him as well as the degree of
specialisation of the information, i.e., if the person is an art expert, he
will desire more detail than the occasional museum visitor.</p><p>There are two approaches to organising data in a real to virtual world
mapping: a so-called <i>logical</i> approach and a <i>physical</i> approach.
The logical approach is the traditional way, and involves storing all data
relevant to the physical world on a service platform such as a centralised
database. Context information is sent to a person in response to a request
containing the person's location co-ordinates and preferences. In the example
of the virtual museum guide, a person's device transmits its location to the
server, which replies with descriptions of neighbouring artworks.</p><p>The main drawbacks of this approach are scalability and complexity.
Scalability is a problem since we are evolving towards a world with billions
of embedded devices; complexity is a problem since the majority of physical
objects are unrelated, and no management body can cater for the integration of
their data into a service platform. Further, the model of the physical world
must be up to date, so the more dynamic a system is, the more updates are
needed. The services platform quickly becomes a potential bottleneck if it
must deliver services to all people.</p><p>The physical approach does not rely on a digital model of the physical world.
The service is computed wherever the person is located. This is done by
spreading data onto the devices in the physical environment; there are a
sufficient number of embedded systems with wireless transceivers around to
support this approach. Each device manages and stores the data of its
associated object. In this way, data are physically linked to objects, and
there is no need to update a positional database when physical objects move
since the data <i>physically</i> moves with them.</p><p>With the physical approach, computations are done on the personal and
available embedded devices. Devices interact when they are within
communication range. The interactions constitute delivery of service to the
person. Returning to the museum example, data is directly embedded in a
painting's frame. When the visitor's guide meets (connects) to a painting's
devices, it receives the information about the painting and displays it.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid16"><bodyTitle>Spatial Information Systems</bodyTitle><p>One of the major research efforts in <span class="smallcap" align="left">Aces</span> over the last few years has
been the definition of the Spread programming model to cater for spacial
context. The model is derived from the
Linda <ref xlink:href="#bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/> tuple-space model. Each
information item is a <i>tuple</i>, which is a sequence of typed data items.
For example, <tt>&lt;10, 'Peter', -3.14&gt;</tt> is a tuple where the first element is
the integer 10, the second is the string `"Peter" and the third is the real
value -3.14. Information is addressed using patterns that match one or a set
of tuples present in the tuple-space. An example pattern that matches the
previous tuple is <tt>&lt;int, 'Peter', float&gt;</tt>. The tuple-space model has the
advantage of allowing devices that meet for the first time to exchange data
since there is no notion of names or addresses.</p><p>Data items are not only addressed by their type, but also by the physical
space in which they reside. The size of the space is determined by the
strength of the radio signal of the device. The important difference between
Spread and other tuple-space systems (e.g., Sun's
JavaSpaces <ref xlink:href="#bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>, IBM's T-Space <ref xlink:href="#bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>) is that when
a program issues a matching request, only the tuples filling the <i>physical
space</i> of the requesting program are tested for matching. Thus, though
applications are highly distributed by nature, they only rely on localised
communications; they do not require access to a global communication
infrastructure. Figure <ref xlink:href="#uid17" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/> shows an example of a physical
tuple space, made of tuples arranged in the space and occupying different
spaces.</p><object id="uid17"><table><tr><td><ressource aux="image_1.png" xylemeAttach="1" xlink:href="IMG/phy-tspace" type="float" width="10cm" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="2991821102025"/></td></tr></table><caption>Physical Tuple Space</caption></object><p>As an example of the power of this model, consider two of the applications
that we have developed using it.</p><simplelist><li id="uid18"><p><i>Ubi-bus</i> is a spatial
information application whose role is to help blind and partially blind people
use public transport. When taking a bus, a blind person uses his PDA to signal
his intention to a device embedded in the bus stop; this device then contacts
the bus on the person's behalf. This application illustrates how data is
distributed over the objects of the physical world, and generally, how devices
complement human means of communication.</p></li><li id="uid19"><p><i>Ubi-board</i> is a spatial information application designed for
public electronic billboards. Travel hotspots like airports and major train
stations have an international customer base, so bill-board announcements need
to be made in several languages. In Ubi-bus, a billboard has an embedded
device. When a person comes within communication range of the billboard, his
device sends a request to the billboard asking it to print the message in the
language of the person. In the case where several travellers are in proximity
of the billboard, the board sends a translation of its information message to
each person. The Ubi-board application illustrates personal context in use,
i.e., the choice of natural language, and also how actions can be provoked in
the physical world without explicit intervention by the person.</p></li></simplelist></subsection></subsection><subsection id="uid20"><bodyTitle>Operating System Support</bodyTitle><p>The role of an operating system is to offer an environment for program
execution. It offers programs access to essential services, such as
communication and storage, and thus indirectly to network and disk.
Person-centric computing is characterised by small portable devices that can
be awkward for a person to manipulate. The operating system needs to manage
generally limited resource, in particularly in relation to the network. We
first give some background to the problem of resource management – given its
importance in person-centric computing – before coming back to other
operating system aspects.</p><subsection id="uid21"><bodyTitle>Service Adaptation</bodyTitle><p>Mobile networks are becoming increasingly heterogeneous. Global coverage is
now well provided by 2G and 2.5G cellular systems, and 3G networks (UTMS) are
being deployed in some densely populated areas. Nonetheless, high data rates
(several Mb/s) will not be available everywhere in the near future, so the
delivery of large amounts of information to people on the move will remain
limited and expensive.</p><subsection id="uid22"><bodyTitle>Data Adaptation</bodyTitle><p>Wireless network coverage in mobile systems can be highly variable for reasons
of coverage as well as for reasons related to subscription business models.
This variability suggests that an application must be able to adapt to network
related changes. An application must also be able to adapt to particular
resource limitations of devices it communicates with at any time.</p><p>Ultimately, adaptation manifests itself in the quality and nature of data
exchanged between devices. One solution to adapting data is to transform its
representation in a way that best suits the digital context of host devices.</p><p>For example, depending on the actual behaviour of the system (network
bandwidth, load, etc.), it implies the ability to manipulate different
representations of the same data that are physically different but
semantically equivalent (e.g., the color and black-and-white versions of the
same picture). These representations differ only in quality. For instance,
when transmitting video to a mobile device, the number of frames per second
can be reduced to cater for variable bandwidth, and the size of each frame can
be significantly reduced to cater for the fact that the screen is quite small.
Another example is Web browsing; a mobile device might decide to filter
applets and images from downloaded pages in order to reduce the device CPU
time needed to process the page.</p><p>Data adaptability requires collaboration between the operating system and the
applications <ref xlink:href="#bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>. As the previous examples illustrate, the type of
data adaptation relies on the semantics of the application, so only it can
decide how to adapt to resource changes. It is the role of the operating
system to survey changes in resources, and to inform the application of
important changes so that adaptation can take place in time.</p><p>An unstable connection can temporarily isolate a mobile entity from the rest
of the system. When this happens, the proposed service cannot be properly
delivered. In order to hide disconnections from a person, pre-fetching
techniques can be used: documents are pre-loaded in a local cache of the
mobile device during high connectivity periods. The application therefore
remains operational when a temporal disconnection occurs as all needed
documents have been stored locally in the cache of the device. The data loaded
into the caches are selected based on the personal context, incorporating a
person's preferences, as well as on hints provided by the user and on
information that is automatically tracked (for example a log of all previously
accessed documents).</p></subsection><subsection id="uid23"><bodyTitle>The Pico-cell Architecture</bodyTitle><p>The past few years have witnessed the rise of the cellular networks. These communication systems were designed with a philosophy of <i>any-time any-where</i> service. Users wish to receive and place calls at any location and without delay, to move while talking without interrupting their conversations. This requires ubiquitous coverage, which in turn requires significant infrastructure. A modern cellular system is installed with hundreds of base stations, at a cost of hundreds of millions of euros, in order that a communication link is always available. Such any-time any-where service provision becomes increasingly expensive and suffers from low bandwidth. Covering wide areas with high radio bandwidth requires complex equalization, due to signal attenuation, multi-path fade, and shadowing effects. Sophisticated radio engineering will lead to improved bandwidth, coverage, and mobile access, but this will be expensive, in terms of both capabilities and cost.</p><p>In this context, the ACES project has studied an alternate design for wireless networks where intermittent but very high speed is provided to the network through <i>Pico-cells</i>. The latter consists of a set of access points (APs)-based for example on WLANs cells-, <i>i.e.</i> antennas around of which are defined radio cells with limited range (about 100 meters). Those antennas are discontinuously spread on the network area, thus providing a <i>many-time many-where</i> service. Actually, the idea of coverage discontinuity brings two major advantages. First, as it implies the use of a fewer number of access points, the architecture deployment will be cheaper. Second, radio cells disjunction hypothesis simplifies the radio frequency band management and avoids interference problems.</p><p>Even if this model simplifies network deployment, the connectivity intermittence induces important challenges in order to avoid service disruption. Thus, terminals have to take advantage of the high bandwidth when it is available. For delay tolerant data, a terminal stores data as it passes under a cell. Hence, it may consume the buffered data even when it passes through regions of poor network coverage. Many projects have studied very specific cases where the cells deployment is uniform and data is sent from servers to terminals (down-link). One example of this type of system is studied by WINLAB (Wireless Information Network Laboratory). In this project, cells are equally spaced and the data delivery algorithm is tested in a network with one dimensional system <i>i.e.</i> high ways.</p><object id="uid24"><table><tr><td><ressource aux="image_2.png" xylemeAttach="2" xlink:href="IMG/dcov" type="float" width="4.5cm" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="1906254030004"/></td></tr></table><caption>Pico-cell architecture model</caption></object><p>Our approach is based on a more general case in which cells are distributed according to the envisaged traffic and data can be exchanged in both directions down-link (from servers to terminals) and up-link (from terminals to servers). The main challenge is to provide system mechanisms and efficient services addressing the specific constraints of this architecture: discontinuous coverage, user unconstrained mobility, high user density.
To cope with the discontinuous coverage of the network, we store data (with
caching mechanisms) close to mobile people, just before data delivery. Thus,
the placement policy of data within the architecture is conditioned by
knowledge of people on the move. The goal here is to define a representation
of person mobility in the network architecture, and to use this model for
placing data using limited and customised flooding mechanisms.</p><p>Through this architecture model, we underline the analogy between
heterogeneous mobile networks and multiprocessor architectures (for example
the mobile device can be considered as a processor). This approach allows us
to map and extend existing caching mechanisms, taking into account the
specific constraints of a discontinuous mobile network. This architecture and
the attached mechanisms have been evaluated with a simulation platform (See
section on <i>Software</i>).</p></subsection></subsection><subsection id="uid25"><bodyTitle>Operating Systems for Small Devices</bodyTitle><p>Recent years have seen a huge proliferation of applications developed in the
Java<span class="math" align="left"><sup><hi rend="it">T</hi><hi rend="it">M</hi></sup></span> programming language <ref xlink:href="#bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>. The advantage of Java
is that the language is strongly typed, so programs are protected from the
memory manipulation errors that are frequent with C/C++ applications. Another
reason for its success is that Java environments now possess a rich set of
libraries that are convenient for a wide range of systems programming tasks. A
final, and important, reason for the prevalence of Java is that the Java
compiler transforms programs to a standardised set of high-level assembly-like
instructions called <i>bytecode</i>. Java environments incorporate a virtual
machine that interprets bytecode. The advantage of this is portability: any
platform that runs a Java environment may run a compiled Java program, without
modification. Java environments now exists for mobile phones, pagers, PDAs and
a wide range of embedded and wireless
devices<footnote id="uid26" place="foot" anchored="yes"><ref xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/j2me/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="712478608028">http://java.sun.com/j2me/</ref></footnote>.</p><subsection id="uid27"><bodyTitle>Java Operating Systems</bodyTitle><p>The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Aces</span> research group has been collaborating with <i>Texas
Instruments</i> on the design of a heterogeneous multiprocessor architecture
composed of a dedicated Java bytecode processor (JSM) and ARM processor. This
work led us to design an operating system that is completely written in the
Java programming language, and that can run on any abstract Java bytecode processor platform.</p><p>The advantage of a Java operating system running on an abstract bytecode processor is portability and
safety. Currently, Java environments permit applications to interact with
non-Java code, which is generally referred to as <i>native</i> code. Native
code is used to implement operating system services, drivers as well as legacy
applications. The problem with native code is that it creates an application
dependency on third-party non-Java code. This challenges application
portability since an application on one platform is no longer guaranteed to
run on another platform. Further, native code is not subject to the
type-safety checks of the Java language; this code can therefore compromise
the security of the whole application.</p><p>There have been several R &amp; D efforts to develop Java operating systems and
Java environments written in the Java language, e.g.,
JX <ref xlink:href="#bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>, JNode<footnote id="uid28" place="foot" anchored="yes">http://www.jnode.org</footnote>,
OVM<footnote id="uid29" place="foot" anchored="yes">http://www.ovmj.org</footnote>, Jalapeño <ref xlink:href="#bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>, etc.
These systems still contain native code units. JNode and Jalapeño compile
the system's code base to native code for a host platform processor and OS
pair in an effort to maximise run-time performance. However, this approach
means that no use can be made of any bytecode processor, and the
system requires extra means to protect the Java environment from all imported
native code.</p><p>The idea of a machine that directly implements a language is not new, with
many attempts to build such architectures in the 1970s, e.g., the Burroughs
machine <ref xlink:href="#bid10" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/> designed to run Algol-60 <ref xlink:href="#bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>
and the SAR designed to support Algol-68. Other notable efforts include
Hydra <ref xlink:href="#bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/> from CMU and the iAPX432 from Intel <ref xlink:href="#bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>. The
goal of these projects was to run a programming language directly on a
hardware architecture. This approach provides the obvious benefits of having
the programming language semantics directly implemented by the hardware.
However, these systems had three important drawbacks. First, the
implementation of communication channels to interface between the programming
language and the underlying hardware was complicated. Second, performance was
generally poor. Third, the programming languages chosen lacked the popularity
needed for the machines to reach a critical mass. The Java language does not
suffer from the popularity drawback, and the availability of JSM processors
that execute bytecode is helping to address the performance issue. The
remaining challenge is program-to-hardware communication, and is an issue
being addressed in the <span class="smallcap" align="left">Aces</span> research group.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid30"><bodyTitle>Native Objects and the Java Abstract Machine</bodyTitle><p>A portable Java operating system environment is one where all programs,
services and operating system functions are compiled to bytecode. The only
non-Java, or complementary instruction set architecture (C-ISA), instructions
are those that manipulate attached hardware resources, e.g., keyboard, screen,
communication ports, etc. The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Aces</span> group developed an operating
system model in which devices are represented as Java objects whose methods
can only be invoked by the operating system code (written in Java). These
objects are known as <i>native objects</i>. Their methods are implemented
independently of the Java layers: in microcode for hardware implementations of the
abstract processor, in C or even Java for software implementations.</p><object id="uid31"><table><tr><td><ressource aux="image_3.png" xylemeAttach="3" xlink:href="IMG/javaos" type="float" width="10cm" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="2565804835010"/></td></tr></table><caption>Structure of Java-based Operating System</caption></object><p>The structure of our Java operating system is illustrated in
Figure <ref xlink:href="#uid31" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>. The native objects are placed at the same level as the abstract
bytecode processor. To date, we have developed native objects for a keyboard,
video card and UART serial bus. As with any processor, the bytecode processor
supports the deployment of interrupt handlers so that the operating system
services can manage devices. The next layer is composed of two parts. A Java
services part implements all functionality needed to implement Java programs
that is is not provided by the bytecode; this includes garbage collection of
unused objects, thread scheduling and code verification of classes loaded into
the system. The operating system part contains the device drivers and other OS
functionality written in Java; for instance, we ported a TCP/IP stack and
LCUDI graphics library to Java for integration in this part. The remaining two
layers are common to all Java environments. The presence of the Java
development kit (JDK) means that Java applications can run unaware of the fact
that a bytecode processor is running below them. In particular, user code and
libraries cannot invoke methods on native objects.</p><p>Though our Java operating system is designed to run over a physical bytecode
processor, it can just as easily run over a software emulation of this
processor in native code. In this respect the bytecode processor is an example
of an <i>abstract machine</i>. Implementing this abstract machine is simpler
than implementing a traditional Java virtual machine since only the bytecode
interpretation component needs to be implemented instead of a whole series of
thread and memory management services. Further, this implementation is hidden
from all application and system service developers who can in no way interfere
with the correct functioning of the abstract machine, since their code is
written in Java. Thus, a native implementation of the abstract machine does
not suffer from the portability and security shortfalls that we mentioned
above for existing Java environments.</p><p>We return to our work on Java operating systems in Section <i>New Results</i>
where we detail the recent innovative elements of our work .</p></subsection></subsection></subsection></fondements><logiciels id="uid32"><bodyTitle>Software</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid33"><bodyTitle>Introduction</bodyTitle><p>The research tasks conducted in the ACES project lead to the development
of many softwares. These developments are mainly realized, or at least
initialized within the framework of industrial collaborations, and so they
are attached to the application domains covered by the project.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid34"><bodyTitle>Simulation Platform for Networks with Discontinuous Coverage</bodyTitle><p>The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Aces</span> group developed a network simulator for pico-cell
architectures that is used to analyse flow distribution in networks. This
architecture is described in the <i>New Results</i> section of this report.
The simulator is entirely coded in the Java programming language and uses the
DESMO-J discrete event model. The simulator models all entities required to
study discontinuous coverage network behaviour, including terminals, access
points, admission control, content provision servers, MAC layers, wireless
transmission, protocol cache management as well as different (person) device
mobility models. The main emphasis of our development has been to tailor the
simulator to measuring performance in large-scale networks – the size of
towns where there are hundreds of devices per square kilometers – over periods
of a few hours.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid35"><bodyTitle>Ubi-Board</bodyTitle><p>Ubi-Board is a splitted display system, capable of adapting contextually the content and the
display surface accordingly to the population in the immediate vincinity of a display panel. The
system uses spatial programming in order to determine dominant profiles, such as dominant language
which allows the selection of the appropriate content to display on the main panel. As the main panel
changes, the system synchronously pushes the appropriate content version to users not belonging
to the dominant profile, to be displayed on their personal display (typically cellphones).</p></subsection></logiciels><resultats id="uid36"><bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid37"><bodyTitle>Introduction</bodyTitle><p>The ACES project is currently very active in three main research activities</p><simplelist><li id="uid38"><p>Programming models</p></li><li id="uid39"><p>Discontinuous mobile networks</p></li><li id="uid40"><p>Java Operating Systems</p></li></simplelist><p>In the following we give the major research results we got from these activities.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid41"><bodyTitle>Programming models</bodyTitle><p><b>Participants</b>: Michel Banâtre, Mathieu Bécus, Paul Couderc [contact], Damien Martin-Gutteriez, Mickael LeBaillif, Xavier Le Bourdon</p><p>The ambient computing activity for this year include three main
topics, that we describe in the next sections.</p><subsection id="uid42"><bodyTitle>Geometry and pervasive computing</bodyTitle><p>The role of geometry is important in pervasive computing as we can
derive implicit data organization from spatial properties, and
implicit data processing from mobility. Spatial programming is a
computation model using this approach, allowing simple programming of
pervasive computing application distributed over a set of physical
objects. A Ph. D was completed on this topic, and has be defended by
Julien Pauty in April 2006 <ref xlink:href="#bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>.</p><p>A result of this work is a solution for the problem of atomic
operation in the context of spontaneous communications, such as for
example the atomic token passing between two mobile devices. This
problem has no general solution, due to the inherently unreliable
nature of wireless communication and the limited communication time
implied by device mobility. However, partial solutions to the problem
are proposed, involving a modified two phase commit protocol where
engagement is restricted by a geometrical constraint. This constraint
reduces the zone in which the protocol can start, in order to allow the
completion before the devices be out of reach. We have shown that
although it is not possible to guarantee failure free operation,
acceptable reliability can be achieved for certain applications.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid43"><bodyTitle>Context sensitive systems</bodyTitle><p>The notion of context as it is used in most ubiquitous computing work
is strongly different of the notion of context used in information
system. Typically, context is understood by the ubiquitous computing
community as a set of information charaterizing a physical
situation. The notion of context in information systems corresponds to
the relative location of a given information item, in respect to a
more global set of information. We introduced in the past a unified
definition of context, based on the definition used in information
system, but also covering physical aspects. In this definition, we
consider the physical space as an implicit structure for information
associated to physical objects or region. This definition provides a
support for organizing and navigating an information
collectionimplicitely from the physical space.</p><p>Implementing this definition relies on sensing technologies to collect information from physical objects. We are now using RFID, in combination with other technologies such as Bluetooth and WLAN that we used in in the past. RFID provides the advantage to allow precise spatial sensing, hence allowing more accurate geometrical definition for context settings. These new architectures will be experimented in a collaboration with Aeroports de Paris : Ubi Board, a context sensitive display system that determines the "dominant" profile in its viciny, accordingly to the current majority. This is used to switch the content of the
display in the appropriate language (of the majority), but at the same
time sending localized version of the content to mobile of each user
in a minority.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid44"><bodyTitle>Cooperating objects</bodyTitle><p>The third topic is the cooperation of autonomous objects. With today
proliferation of mobile devices enabled with communication and
multimedia data capture capabilities, large quantity of data
production and processing directly takes place on the move, or in
situation. Heterogenous communication interface and node architecture,
interactions with unknown nodes (hence, under limited trust), data
reliability, global processing over a set of nodes are some of the
challenging issues raised by cooperating objects. Wireless sensor
networks have similar issues, in addition to exacerbated energy and
resources constraints.</p><p>We were involved in the Embedded WiSents European cooperation, as a
study leader regarding programming abstractions and system
architecture for cooperating objects.</p><p>Key to the successful and widespread deployment of cooperating objects
and sensor network technologies is the provision of appropriate
programming abstractions and the establishment of efficient system
architectures able to deal with the complexity of such
systems. Programming abstractions shield the programmer from the
``system specific details'' and allow the developer to think in terms of
the concrete application problem rather then in terms of the
system. This is also true for traditional distributed systems, where
numerous software frameworks and middleware architectures are crucial
to perform an integrated computing task. Such frameworks and
middleware are based on programming models such as distributed objects
or events. These conventional and successful distributed programming
abstractions can, however, not be simply applied to cooperating
objects or sensor networks, due to the differences existing among the
latter and the former systems.</p><p>We are also involved in another cooperation, the french ACI Mosaic,
which study the problem of cooperative backup of mobile devices. The
first objective is to define an automatic data back-up and recovery
service based on mutual cooperation between mobile devices with no
prior trust relationships. Such a service aims to ensure continuous
availability of critical data managed by mobile devices that are
particularly prone to energy depletion, physical damage, loss or
theft. The basic idea is to allow a mobile device to exploit
accessible peer devices to manage backups of its critical data. The
implementation of such a service by cooperation between devices with
no prior trust relationship is far from trivial since new threats are
introduced: (a) selfish devices may refuse to cooperate, (b) backup
repository devices may themselves fail or attack the confidentiality
or integrity of the backup data; (c) rogue devices may seek to deny
service to peer devices by flooding them with fake backup requests;
etc <ref xlink:href="#bid15" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>.</p><p>Dealing with these threats is the second objective of the project. We
are studying mechanisms for managing trust in cooperative services
between mutually suspicious devices. Of particular interest are
mechanisms based on reputation (for a priori confidence-rating and a
posteriori accountability) and rewards (for cooperation
incitation). In the sparse ephemeral networks of devices considered,
these mechanisms can rely neither on accessibility to trusted third
parties nor on connectivity of a majority of the considered population
of devices. Self-carried reputation and rewards are therefore of prime
interest.</p><p>In this study, we are focused on the energy issues of the backup
protocol, and on analysing the data production and use pattern of
typical mobile applications.</p><p>Two new perspectives around cooperating objects are being developed now
- Cooperation of robots, where the physical space is tagged with instructions and/or data. We participate to a new European project, Roboswarm, on this research theme.
- Spontaneous collaboration of capture devices (such as video/sound sensors), where mobile devices improve the reliability and quality of their local capture capabilities by collaborating with other nodes.
</p></subsection></subsection><subsection id="uid45"><bodyTitle>Discontinous Mobile Networks</bodyTitle><p><b>Participants</b>: Fabien Allard, Carole Bonan, Azza Jedidi, Antoine Luu, Ronan Ménard, Mazen Tlais, Frédéric Weis [contact]</p><p>During this past year, we designed an architecture capable of supporting video
streaming over a pico-cell type infrastructure. The core idea is to insert a
new component, called an <i>access controller</i>, that acts as a connector
between the IP infrastructure and high-bandwidth cells. The access controller
is able to efficiently schedule (distribute) streams to different mobile
nodes. Recently, we have extended this mechanism so that video streams are
distinguished from less time-critical applications, e.g., Web, file transfer,
etc.</p><subsection id="uid46"><bodyTitle>Continuous data delivery</bodyTitle><p>Our first goal consists in designing a scalable unicast streaming service for discontinuous networks. On the one hand, streaming servers are usually located in classical IP networks. Such networks are submitted to many constraints, like bandwidth variations. On the other hand, mobile terminals evolve in wireless discontinuous coverage areas, constituted of several access points. The first idea we propose in the context of such networks, is to design and introduce an intermediate equipment that will catch the video flows sent by the content server, and then efficiently distribute (<i>i.e.</i>schedule) them to mobile terminals in the network according to their radio conditions. This equipment is called the <b>Access Controller</b> (AC).</p><p>The AC acts as a cache which temporarily stores the part of the flow to be delivered. More precisely the AC is provided with many caches. Each of them is related with a single streaming request and contains the part of the flow to be sent to the terminal. A terminals also contains a cache to store some parts of the flow, in order to consume it while crossing out of coverage areas, and to avoid service disruption. And in the AC, a scheduling policy is implemented for classifying flows in priority queues, depending (1) on terminal positions in the radio cells and on (2) terminal cache contents. Simulations have highlighted the efficiency of the scheduling policy implemented in the AC.</p><p>Based on this architecture, a thesis has been defended by Carole Bonan on December 2006 <ref xlink:href="#bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid47"><bodyTitle>Improving wireless network capacity by introducing logical discontinuous coverage</bodyTitle><p>We also showed that the mechanisms defined initially in the framework of discontinuous coverage networks can be easily extended to the context of classical continuous coverage networks (like for example 3<sup>rd</sup> generation UMTS networks). In such networks, available radio bandwidth is highly varying, depending on terminal positions. <i>High bandwidth areas</i> are similar to Pico-cells coverage areas, and <i>low bandwidth areas</i> can be assimilated to previous out-of-coverage areas.</p><p>Actually, our idea is to insert into a continuous network an equipment called <b>anchor point</b>. The latter acts as an AC: its goal is to favour data transfers when terminals are located in high bandwidth areas. We have demonstrated through simulations that avoiding data transfers in low bandwidth areas improves system scalability. For that we have evaluated the number of service disruptions according to users density. The result is that the network capacity (a fixed users density without service disruption) is improved of about 300 % (see figure <ref xlink:href="#uid48" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/> when an anchor point is present in the network <ref xlink:href="#bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>.</p><object id="uid48"><table><tr><td><ressource aux="image_4.png" xylemeAttach="4" xlink:href="IMG/eval" type="float" width="12.0cm" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="1300235374014"/></td></tr></table><caption>Evolution of service disruptions using an anchor point</caption></object><p>Finally this new logically discontinuous vision of the cellular networks makes our architecture model (one AC / anchor point inserted between terminals and data servers) fit to classical 3<sup>rd</sup> generation networks, which are continuously covered but subject to important bandwidth fluctuations, as well to Pico-cells networks.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid49"><bodyTitle>Design of a data storage model</bodyTitle><p>As we have said before, several studies are done to provide efficient services in the down-link (from servers to terminals). We now strong believe that many interesting services may exist in the up-link. The idea is to benefit from our network architecture, mainly, the existence of caches in ACs and terminals to provide new (up-link) services. The latter are possible thanks to the advances in the mobile terminals. Mobile phones with cameras are in widespread use. PDAs and laptops have WiFi interfaces for mobile computing. A wireless device can be used for sending/receiving photos, videos, emails. Many problems appear because of the mobile environment and technological limitations. For example, the radio bandwidth, network connectivity, storage capacity. Users want to move in different areas without worrying about their applications. For instance, a tourist in Paris takes photos of the "Eiffel tower" with his digital camera, and then he moves to take photos of the historic "Versailles palace", but he has not got any free memory storage left. The tourist wants to enjoy the view and does not like to search for a high bandwidth connection or an extra memory storage. Similar problems appear with many other applications like movies, video clips and shared memory storage.</p><p>In this context, we propose a framework that represents a new distributed storage model that implicitly exchanges data with the closest AC when a high bandwidth connection is available. Terminals store data in their local caches, modify them while disconnected, and synchronize them with the closest AC when a high bandwidth connection is detected. For doing so, we propose a communication model adequate with the proposed architecture. It is based on the client server model taking into account the distributed and hierarchical architecture. ACs are used to temporary store incoming data from terminals and servers. The delay time the data stay in an AC depends on a class of service <b>(CoS)</b> associated with data. For example, a tourist may need to send photos to his family immediately
or as soon as possible. Another tourist may only need a shared memory for his album without sending the photos at all <ref xlink:href="#bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>.</p><p>All the system mechanisms needed for the storage model have been specified by Mazen Tlais (last year PhD). We have also identified some applications that can exploit the up-link and the CoS principle. At present our goal is (1) to integrate these mechanisms with the scheduling policy already implemented in ACs, and (2) to demonstrate the pertinence of this approach by experimenting identified applications.</p></subsection></subsection><subsection id="uid50"><bodyTitle>Java Operating Systems</bodyTitle><p><b>Participants</b> : Fabien Allard, Michel Banâtre [contact], Arnaud Guiton, Cédric Mosch,
Jean-Paul Routeau, Claude Vittoria, Pierre Duquesne, Ciarán Bryce.</p><p>Our work on Java operating systems has been going on for four years now. At
the end of 2004, we had completed the design of a Java operating system for
the underlying Java processor and proposed the idea of <i>native objects</i>
to encapsulate hardware devices. We had started to implement the system over a
Linux platform and, in this context, implemented the TCP/IP stack in the Java
language. In addition to our work with Texas Instruments, our group has also
been collaborating on a Java Specification Request for resource management,
and on a security model for Java multi-tasking environments with researchers
from Sun Microsystems.</p><subsection id="uid51"><bodyTitle>Pure Java Platforms</bodyTitle><p>Last year (2005), we concentrated on the
specification of our Java abstract machine around the bytecode processor. In
particular, we formalised the integration of native objects and interrupt
handling into the machine. This leads to the layered operating system model
that is illustrated in Figure <ref xlink:href="#uid31" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>. In this model, the methods of
native objects are coded as a special bytecode instructions that are micro-coded
using the instruction set (C-ISA) supported by the associated hardware device.</p><p>There has been a considerable amount of implementation work on the project. We
started coding a software implementation of the bytecode processor based on
the K virtual machine (KVM); this yielded what we name the <span class="smallcap" align="left">Kvm
Bytecode Processor</span> (KBP). Native objects were developed for a frame-buffer
based screen and a keyboard. Device drivers were written in the Java
programming language for a UART serial bus, the screen and keyboard devices,
and for an infrared (IRDA) device. At the Java service layer (c.f.,
Figure <ref xlink:href="#uid31" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/>), we developed a thread scheduler in Java for the CLDC
variant of the Java (J2ME) environment and at the operating system services
layer, we developed a protocol stack for the GPRS mobile phone protocol and
integrated this with the IP stack that we developed last year.</p><p>Two PhD students are currently working on the our Java operating system
project. <i>Cédric Motsch</i> is integrating multi-tasking
(for running multiple applications) over the operating system and wrote a
cross-application scheduler. The main innovation in the platform is the introduction of
application domains. A domain can encapsulate an application and its JDK and can be
isolated from other domains. Restricted sharing between domains is nonetheless possible.
<i>Arnaud Guiton</i> is currently studying memory management for the Java platform.</p><p>One of the new topics that we began studying this year is software patching. The code base of systems and applications are dynamic: they continue to change even after delivery of the software to clients. These changes are implemented through the application of <i>patches</i>. Though their primary necessity is to fix security holes and discovered bugs, patches are even used to add new functionality. Patching requires a formal framework that ensures that modifications can be safely made to running applications.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid52"><bodyTitle>Resource Management</bodyTitle><p>Independently of the Texas Instruments collaboration, the group participated in a Java Specification Request for a resource management interface for the Java platform. Resources include CPU, heap memory, network bandwidth; a systems programmer can define further abstract resources, e.g., database connections, servlet invocations, etc. Monitoring resource consumption and imposing limits on consumption are key requirements for any platform. Until now, no such mechanism existed for the Java platform. The JSR was in progress for nearly two years, and its output is a Java API and reference implementation. The API specification has now entered a public review stage. In the context of JSR 284, we collaborated with representatives from Google, IBM, BEA Systems, Intel, Nokia, Siemens, Motorola and EPFL-Switzerland. This collaboration led to the final draft of the specification, published in December 2006.</p></subsection></subsection></resultats><contrats id="uid53"><bodyTitle>Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid54"><bodyTitle>National contracts</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid55"><bodyTitle>Aéroport de Paris</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid56"><p>Title: Conception et mise au point de pilotes de services aéroportuaires reposant sur les technologies de l'informatique diffuse dveloppées par l'INRIA- UR Rennes.</p></li><li id="uid57"><p>Partner: <i>Aéroport de Paris</i></p></li><li id="uid58"><p>Starting: 01/11/2006, ending : 15/02/2007</p></li></simplelist></subsection><subsection id="uid59"><bodyTitle>TV mobile &lt;&lt;sans limite&gt;&gt; (TVMSL)</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid60"><p>Partner : Alcatel Mobile Broadcast,
Alcatel Alenia Space
Alcatel,
DiBcom,
Sagem Communication,
TeamCast,
Radio Frequency Systems,
UDcast,
CEA-Leti,
Inria-Rennes,
CNRS-L2S</p></li><li id="uid61"><p>Starting: 01/11/206, ending : 30/04/2009</p></li></simplelist><p>The objective of this contract is to design and evaluate inovative caching mechanisms
to distribute H.264 flows in future hybrid DVB-H+ infrastructure (satellite + terrestrial).</p></subsection><subsection id="uid62"><bodyTitle>Texas Instruments </bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid63"><p>Number: 198C2730031303202</p></li><li id="uid64"><p>Title: Real time Java Distributed Processing Environment</p></li><li id="uid65"><p>Related Research activity: see section <ref xlink:href="#uid50" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/></p></li><li id="uid66"><p>Partner: <i>Texas Instruments</i></p></li><li id="uid67"><p>Founding: <i>Texas Instruments</i></p></li><li id="uid68"><p>Starting: 01/10/1998, ending : 30/09/2001</p></li><li id="uid69"><p>Extension starting: 01/10/2001, ending : 30/09/2003</p></li><li id="uid70"><p>Extension starting: 01/10/2003, ending : 30/09/2006</p></li></simplelist><p>The objective of that contract is to design and build a Java
runtime suitable for embedded platforms on Texas Instruments
hardware architectures.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid71"><bodyTitle>Alcatel</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid72"><p>Number: 101C078</p></li><li id="uid73"><p>Title: Advanced service delivery for 4G discontinuous networks</p></li><li id="uid74"><p>Related Research activity: see section <ref xlink:href="#uid45" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/></p></li><li id="uid75"><p>Partner: <i>Alcatel</i></p></li><li id="uid76"><p>Founding: <i>Alcatel</i></p></li><li id="uid77"><p>Starting: 01/09/2002, ending : 30/10/2004</p></li><li id="uid78"><p>Extension starting: 01/11/2004, ending : 31/10/2007</p></li></simplelist><p>The objective of that contract is to design, build and experiment an efficient
service data delivery in heterogeneous mobile networks. The targeted solution
has to be distributed between the network components and the mobile terminal.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid79"><bodyTitle>JCDecaux</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid80"><p>Number: Inria 401</p></li><li id="uid81"><p>Title: Tuple-ware,</p></li><li id="uid82"><p>Related research activity: see section <ref xlink:href="#uid41" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3512915321001"/></p></li><li id="uid83"><p>Partner: <i>JCDecaux</i></p></li><li id="uid84"><p>Founding: <i>JCdecaux</i></p></li><li id="uid85"><p>Starting: 01/11/2004, ending 31/05/2005</p></li></simplelist><p>The goal of this contract was to implement a pilot (named Tuple-ware), in order to help the JCDecaux company
to evaluate the potential of ambient computing services based on ACES technologies in the area of street furniture and billboard.</p></subsection></subsection></contrats><international id="uid86"><bodyTitle>Other Grants and Activities</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid87"><bodyTitle>European actions</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid88"><bodyTitle>European Project: Roboswarm</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid89"><p>Title: Robot Swarms</p></li><li id="uid90"><p>Proposal/contract no: 045255</p></li><li id="uid91"><p>Tallinna Tehnikalikool- Estonie, ELIKO Tehnoloogia Arenduskeskus- Estonie,
Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique- UR Rennes,
TEKNILLINEN KORKEAKOULU- Finlande,
OULUN YLIOPISTO- Finlande,
FUNDACION FATRONIK- Espagne,
KTH - Kungliga Tekniska Hgskolan Royal Institute of Technology- Sude,
IDMIND-ENGENHARIA DE SISTEMAS, LDA -Portugal,
Universita degli Studi di Genova -Italie</p></li><li id="uid92"><p>Starting: November 2006, ending: April 2009</p></li></simplelist><p>Roboswarm is an EU project that started in November 2006 in which ACES is a participant. The goal of the project is to develop an open knowledge environment for self-configurable, low-cost and robust robot swarms usable in everyday applications. Advances in the state-of-the art of networked robotics are proposed through introduction of a local and global knowledge base for ad hoc communication within a low-cost swarm of autonomous robots operating in the surrounding smart IT infrastructure. The ACES group was invited into this consortium due to its experience with ad hoc (ambient) network environments.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid93"><bodyTitle>Coordinated Action: Embedded WiSeNts</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid94"><p>Title: Cooperating Embedded Systems for Exploration and Control featuring Wireless Sensor Networks</p></li><li id="uid95"><p>Partners: Technische Universität Berlin (Germany), University of
Cambridge (UK), University of Copenhagen (Denmark), Swedish Insitute of
Computer Science (Sweden), University Twente (Netherlands), Yeditepe
University (Turkey), Consorzio Interuniversitario Nazionale per
l'Informatica (Italy), University of Padua (Italy), Swiss Federal
Institute of Technology Zurich (Switzerland), Asociacion de
Investigacion y CooperacionIndustrial de Andalucoa (Spain), Institut
National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique (INRIA),
Universität Stuttgart (Germany)</p></li><li id="uid96"><p>Starting: September 2004, ending: December 2006</p></li></simplelist><p>Embedded WiSeNts aims to increase the awareness and to find out a vision
as well as a researh roadmap towards wireless sensors networks of
cooperating embedded systems, within the academic community and, most
importantly, within the manufacturers of proper technologies as well as
potential users community.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid97"><bodyTitle>NoE Resist</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid98"><p>Title: Resilence and Survability for IST</p></li><li id="uid99"><p>Head: LAAS</p></li><li id="uid100"><p>Starting: beginning of 2006</p></li></simplelist><p>The NoE ReSIST (Resilence and Survability for IST) will focus on the following four objectives in addressing the scalability of dependability and security via resilience:</p><simplelist><li id="uid101"><p>Integration of teams of researchers so that the fundamental topics concerning scalably resilient ubiquitous systems are addressed by a critical mass of co-operative, multi-disciplinary research.</p></li><li id="uid102"><p>Identification, in an international context, of the key research directions induced on the supporting ubiquitous systems by the requirement for trust and confidence in AmI.</p></li><li id="uid103"><p>Production of significant research results that pave the way for scalably resilient ubiquitous systems.</p></li><li id="uid104"><p>Promotion and propagation of a resilience culture in university curricula and in engineering best practices.</p></li></simplelist></subsection></subsection><subsection id="uid105"><bodyTitle>French initiative for research in security and informatics</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid106"><bodyTitle>ACI: Mosaic</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid107"><p>Title: Mobile System Availability Integrity and Confidentiality</p></li><li id="uid108"><p>Partners: Institut Eurecom, Institut de Recherche en Informatique et
Systèmes Aléatoires (IRISA), Laboratoire d'Analyse et d'Architecture des
Systèmes (LAAS)</p></li><li id="uid109"><p>Starting: September 2004, to August 2007</p></li></simplelist><p>The MoSAIC project is studying new fault tolerance and security mechanisms
for mobile wireless devices in ambiant intelligence applications. We focus
on sparse self-organized networks, using mostly one-hop wireless
communication.</p></subsection></subsection></international><diffusion id="uid110"><bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid111"><bodyTitle>Animation of the scientific community</bodyTitle><subsection id="uid112"><bodyTitle>Program committees</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid113"><p>PC member of the International Workshop on Privacy and Security
in Agent-based Collaborative Environments, PSACE 2006. (C. Bryce)</p></li><li id="uid114"><p>PC member of 2007 ACM Symposium on Applied Computing, Track Security. (C. Bryce)</p></li><li id="uid115"><p>PC member for the 5th Conference on Security and Network Architectures (SAR 2006), Mont de Marsan, France, 2006. (C. Bryce)</p></li><li id="uid116"><p>PC member of Algotel 2007, <i>9ème rencontres francophones sur les aspects algorithmiques de télécommunications</i>. (F. Weis)</p></li><li id="uid117"><p>PC member for the Fourth International Conference on Cooperative Internet Computing (CIC2006) Hong Kong, China, 25-27 Oct 2006. (M. Banâtre)</p></li><li id="uid118"><p>PC member for the 3rd European Workshop on Wireless Sensor Networks (EWSN), ETH Zurich, Switzerland, February 13 - 15, 2006. (M. Banâtre)</p></li><li id="uid119"><p>PC member for the 18th International Symposium on Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Communications, Athens, 3-7 September 2007. (M. Banâtre)</p></li><li id="uid120"><p>PC member for the 5th IFIP Workshop on Software Technologies for Future Embedded &amp; Ubiquitous Systems (SEUS 2007, part of ISORC 2007). (P. Couderc)</p></li><li id="uid121"><p>PC member for Self adaptability and self management of context-aware systems, (part of ICAS 2006). (P. Couderc)</p></li></simplelist></subsection><subsection id="uid122"><bodyTitle>Organizing and reviewing activities</bodyTitle><p>Ciarán Bryce is a member of the expert scientific committee for the ANR (<i>Agence national de recherche</i>)
Global Security program.</p><p>Michel Banâtre is member of the scientific committee of the "encyclopedie des systèmes d'information" (Vuibert) and scientific leader of the section
related to Architectures and Operating Systems (end of 2005).</p></subsection></subsection><subsection id="uid123"><bodyTitle>National and international working groups</bodyTitle><p>Participation to the GdR I3 (Information - Interaction - Intelligence),
group Mobility and Ubiquitous Computing (F. Weis)</p></subsection><subsection id="uid124"><bodyTitle>Teaching activities</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid125"><p>Ifsic</p><simplelist><li id="uid126"><p>Responsability of the optional lecture on Operating Systems in masters in Computer Science (M. Banâtre, P. Couderc,
F. Weis),</p></li><li id="uid127"><p>Responsibility of the lecture on Ambient Computing and Distributed Operating Systems in "Diic 3 ARC" (final year of masters)
(M. Banâtre, P. Couderc and F. Weis),</p></li></simplelist></li><li id="uid128"><p>Ecole des Mines de Nantes</p><simplelist><li id="uid129"><p>Responsability of the lecture on distributed systems (final year of masters) computer science department (M. Banâtre),</p></li></simplelist></li><li id="uid130"><p>INSA of Rennes</p><simplelist><li id="uid131"><p>Responsibility of the lecture on Ambient Computing and Distributed Operating Systems (final year of masters)
computer science department (M. Banâtre).</p></li><li id="uid132"><p>6 hours of lectures on Computer Security to final year engineering students (C. Bryce).</p></li></simplelist></li><li id="uid133"><p>University of Rennes I, UFR "Structure et Propriétés de la
Matière", Lecture in DESS "DRI" (French equivalent of Master's
Degree) on home networking (F. Weis).</p></li><li id="uid134"><p>ENST Bretagne, Lecture on Wireless LANs (final years of masters) (F.
Weis).</p></li><li id="uid135"><p>ENSEIRB (Bordeaux), Conference on Mobile communications and ambient computing, final year of masters,
October 2006 (M. Banâtre).</p></li></simplelist><p>F. Weis participates to the computer science <i>commissions de
spécialistes</i> of universities and schools: Université de Lille 1.</p></subsection><subsection id="uid136"><bodyTitle>Internship supervision</bodyTitle><p>We have supervised the following internships in 2006:</p><simplelist><li id="uid137"><p>Julien Bigot (Engineer student, INSA Rennes)</p></li><li id="uid138"><p>Azza Jedidi (Engineer student, ENSEIRB Bordeaux)</p></li></simplelist></subsection><subsection id="uid139"><bodyTitle>Patents</bodyTitle><simplelist><li id="uid140"><p><i>Dispositif de communication local à selection sur base contextuelle</i>. January 2006 (Demande PCT/FR0601031). Patent improving the PCT/FR01/01409 in the context of the RFID technology.</p></li></simplelist></subsection><subsection id="uid141"><bodyTitle>Industrial transfers</bodyTitle><p>The strong point of the group is its <i>research methodology</i>. We have consistently sought industrial collaboration for our research in order to validate our assumptions and/or to ensure that solutions can be used in a real world context. Thus, our work on ambient computing models has led to the sale of several patents, including a major technology transfer to JCDecaux – the major world-wide billboard provider. Our work on continuous service provision has been done in collaboration with Alcatel, and our work on Java operating systems has been conducted in collaboration with Texas Instruments, Rennes.</p><p>The group oversaw the creation of UbiSphere in January 2006 based on our ambient computing technology. The company is currently an INRIA incubator, and will remain so until the end of 2007.</p><p>From November 2004 to May 2005, the group was contracted by JCDecaux to implement a pilot (named Tuple-ware), in order to help the JCDecaux company to evaluate the potential of ambient computing services based on ACES technologies in the area of street furniture and billboard. This collaboration led to JCDecaux buying our patent and software in February 2006.</p><p>From November 2006 to February 2007, the group has been commissioned by ADP (<b>Aéroports de Paris (ADP)</b>) to design and implement a pilot of an ambient system, based on the group's technology, for use in airport environments.</p></subsection></diffusion><biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" titre="Bibliography" numero="10"><biblStruct id="bid23" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Informatique diffuse : des concepts à la réalité</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Banâtre</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">C.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Bryce</surname><initial>C.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">P.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Couderc</surname><initial>P.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weis</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName></author><note type="bnote" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">to appear</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName TEIform="orgName">Hermes Publishing</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2007</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">book</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:BANATRE07a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid24" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Cooperating Embedded Systems and Wireless Sensor Networks</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Banâtre</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">A.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Ollero</surname><initial>A.</initial></persName></author><note type="bnote" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">to appear</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName TEIform="orgName">Hermes Publishing</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2007</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">book</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:BANATRE07b</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid26" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Les systèmes d'exploitation</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">C.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Bryce</surname><initial>C.</initial></persName></author><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName TEIform="orgName">Vuibert Encyclopedia</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2006</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">book</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:BRYCE07a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid25" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Embedded WiSeNts Research Roadmap</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">P.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Couderc</surname><initial>P.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Banâtre</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName></author><note type="bnote" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">co-authors with the Embedded Wisents consortium</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName TEIform="orgName">Logos Verlag Berlin</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2007</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">book</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:BANATRE07c</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid16" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Délivrance continue de données dans un réseau sans fil à couverture discontinue</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">C.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Bonan</surname><initial>C.</initial></persName></author><note type="typdoc" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ph. D. Thesis</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName type="school" TEIform="orgName">Université de Rennes I</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">december</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2006</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">phdthesis</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:BONAN06a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid14" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Rôle de la géométrie en informatique diffuse : programmation des applications et navigation contextuelle</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">J.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Pauty</surname><initial>J.</initial></persName></author><note type="typdoc" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ph. D. Thesis</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName type="school" TEIform="orgName">Université de Rennes I</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">February</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2006</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">phdthesis</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:PAUTY06</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid19" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Distributed communication model in hierarchical infostations systems</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Tlais</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weis</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience</title><note type="bnote" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">To appear</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2007</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:TLAIS07a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid27" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Spontaneous Hotspots: Sharing Context-Dependant Resources Using Bluetooth</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">X.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Lebourdon</surname><initial>X.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">P.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Couderc</surname><initial>P.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Banâtre</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Proc. of International Conference on Autonomic and Autonomous Systems (ICAS 2006), Santa Clara, CA, USA</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">July</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2006</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">inproceedings</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:LEBOURDON06a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid15" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Increasing Data Resilience of Mobile Devices with a Collaborative Backup</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">D.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Martin-Guillerez</surname><initial>D.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Banâtre</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">P.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Couderc</surname><initial>P.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Proc. of International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN'06), Philadelphia, PA, USA</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">June</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2006</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">inproceedings</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:MARTIN06a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid21" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Mobility prediction in 4G D-cov Networks</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Tlais</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weis</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">C.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Bonan</surname><initial>C.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Proc. of the 1st IEEE International Workshop on Peformance Analysis and Enhancement of Wireless Networks (PAEMN'06), Vienna, Austria</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">April</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2006</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">inproceedings</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:TLAIS06a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid20" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Centralized Mobility Prediction Support in a Hierarchical Architecture</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Tlais</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weis</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Proc. of the International Conference on Wireless and Mobile Communications (ICWMC'06), Bucharest, Romania</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">August</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2006</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">inproceedings</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:TLAIS05a</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid22" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Caching and scheduling mechanisms for H.264 video flow delivery over discontinuous coverage wireless networks</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">A.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Jedidi</surname><initial>A.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weis</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName></author><note type="bnote" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">To appear, currently under NDA screening by Alcatel</note><note type="typdoc" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Technical report</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName type="institution" TEIform="orgName">IRISA</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">January</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2007</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">techreport</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:JEDIDI07</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid17" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Improving wireless network capacity by introducing logical discontinuous coverage</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">A.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Luu</surname><initial>A.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weis</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">R.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Menard</surname><initial>R.</initial></persName></author><note type="bnote" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">To be published in 2007, currently under NDA screening by Alcatel</note><note type="typdoc" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Technical report</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName type="institution" TEIform="orgName">IRISA</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">January</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2007</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">techreport</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:LUU07</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid18" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Data storage model in infostation systems</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Tlais</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weis</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName></author><note type="bnote" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">To appear, currently under NDA screening by Alcatel</note><note type="typdoc" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Technical report</note><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName type="institution" TEIform="orgName">IRISA</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">January</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2007</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">techreport</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">year</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">cite:TLAIS07</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid9" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Implementing Jalapeño in Java</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Bowen</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Alpern</surname><initial>B.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">C. R.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Attanasio</surname><initial>C. R.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">John J.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Barton</surname><initial>J. J.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Anthony</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Cocchi</surname><initial>A.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Susan Flynn</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Hummel</surname><initial>S. F.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Derek</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Lieber</surname><initial>D.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Ton</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Ngo</surname><initial>T.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Mark</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Mergen</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Janice C.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Shepherd</surname><initial>J. C.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Stephen</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Smith</surname><initial>S.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Proceedings of the Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applications</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1999</year></dateStruct><biblScope type="pages" TEIform="biblScope">314–324</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">inproceedings</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:1999:oopsla:alpern</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid7" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">The Java Programming Language</title><title level="s" TEIform="title">The Java Series</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Ken</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Arnold</surname><initial>K.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">James</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Gosling</surname><initial>J.</initial></persName></author><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName TEIform="orgName">Addison-Wesley</orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1996</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">book</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:Arnold:96:TJPL</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid0" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Embedding the Internet</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Deborah</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Estrin</surname><initial>D.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Ramesh</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Govindan</surname><initial>R.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">John</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Heidemann</surname><initial>J.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">Communications of the ACM</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><biblScope type="volume" TEIform="biblScope">43</biblScope><biblScope type="number" TEIform="biblScope">5</biblScope><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">May</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2000</year></dateStruct><biblScope type="pages" TEIform="biblScope">39–41</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:EmbedInter</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid4" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">JavaSpaces Principles, Patterns, and Practice</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Eric</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Freeman</surname><initial>E.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Susanne</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Hupfer</surname><initial>S.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Ken</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Arnold</surname><initial>K.</initial></persName></author><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName TEIform="orgName">Addison-Wesley<address TEIform="address"><addrLine TEIform="addrLine">Reading, MA, USA</addrLine></address></orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1999</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">book</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:Freeman:1999:JPP</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid3" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Generative Communication in Linda</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">David</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Gelernter</surname><initial>D.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">TOPLAS</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><biblScope type="volume" TEIform="biblScope">7</biblScope><biblScope type="number" TEIform="biblScope">1</biblScope><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">jan</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1985</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:gelernter:generative-communication</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid1" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">The Application of Mobile Computing and Technology to Health Care Services</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Khawar</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Hameed</surname><initial>K.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">Telematics and Informatics</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><biblScope type="volume" TEIform="biblScope">20</biblScope><biblScope type="number" TEIform="biblScope">2</biblScope><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2003</year></dateStruct><biblScope type="pages" TEIform="biblScope">99–106</biblScope><ref xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0736-5853(02)00018-7" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="1969565596021">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0736-5853(02)00018-7</ref></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:journals/tele/Hameed03</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid6" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Agile application-aware adaptation for mobility</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">B.D.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Noble</surname><initial>B.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Satyanarayanan</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">J.E.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Tilton</surname><initial>J.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">J.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Flinn</surname><initial>J.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">K.R.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Walker</surname><initial>K.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">Proceedings of the 16th Symposium on Operating Systems Principles</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1997</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:noble</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid8" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">The JX Operating System</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Christian</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Wawersich</surname><initial>C.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Jrgen</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Kleinder</surname><initial>J.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Meik</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Felser</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">Michael</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Golm</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName></author><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">April 22</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">2002</year></dateStruct><ref xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/561091.html" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xyref="3147309242018">http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/561091.html</ref></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">misc</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:oai:CiteSeerPSU:561091</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid2" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">Some Computer Science Issues in Ubiquitous Computing</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Weiser</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">Communication of the ACM</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><biblScope type="volume" TEIform="biblScope">(7)36</biblScope><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1993</year></dateStruct><biblScope type="pages" TEIform="biblScope">75-83</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:weiser2</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid11" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">An introduction to ALGOL 60</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">M.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Woodger</surname><initial>M.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">The Computer Journal</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><biblScope type="volume" TEIform="biblScope">3</biblScope><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">July</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1960</year></dateStruct><biblScope type="pages" TEIform="biblScope">67–75</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:Woodger:bcs:cj:1960</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid12" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">HYDRA: The Kernel of a Multiprocessor Operating System</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">W.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Wulf</surname><initial>W.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">E.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Cohen</surname><initial>E.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">W.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Corwin</surname><initial>W.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">A.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Jones</surname><initial>A.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">R.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Levin</surname><initial>R.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">F.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Pollack</surname><initial>F.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">Communications of the ACM, CACM</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><biblScope type="volume" TEIform="biblScope">17</biblScope><biblScope type="number" TEIform="biblScope">6</biblScope><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><month full="yes" TEIform="month">June</month><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1974</year></dateStruct><biblScope type="pages" TEIform="biblScope">337–345</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:CCJLPW74</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid5" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><analytic TEIform="analytic"><title level="a" TEIform="title">T Spaces</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">P.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Wyckoff</surname><initial>P.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">S.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">McLaughry</surname><initial>S.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">T.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Lehman</surname><initial>T.</initial></persName><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName">D.</foreName><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Ford</surname><initial>D.</initial></persName></author></analytic><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="j" TEIform="title">IBM Systems Journal</title><imprint TEIform="imprint"><biblScope type="volume" TEIform="biblScope">37</biblScope><biblScope type="number" TEIform="biblScope">3</biblScope><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1998</year></dateStruct><biblScope type="pages" TEIform="biblScope">454–474</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">article</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:WMLF98</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid13" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Introduction to the iAPX 432 Architecture</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName"/><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">(Intel Corp.)</surname><initial/></persName></author><imprint TEIform="imprint"><publisher TEIform="publisher"><orgName TEIform="orgName">Intel Corporation<address TEIform="address"><addrLine TEIform="addrLine">Santa Clara, CA</addrLine></address></orgName></publisher><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1981</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">book</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:Corp.81</note></biblStruct><biblStruct id="bid10" default="NO" TEIform="biblStruct"><monogr TEIform="monogr"><title level="m" TEIform="title">Burroughs B6700 Information Processing Systems Reference Manual</title><author TEIform="author"><persName TEIform="persName"><foreName full="yes" TEIform="foreName"/><surname full="yes" TEIform="surname">Burroughs</surname><initial/></persName></author><imprint TEIform="imprint"><dateStruct full="yes" TEIform="dateStruct"><year full="yes" TEIform="year">1972</year></dateStruct></imprint></monogr><note type="classification" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">misc</note><note type="from" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">foot</note><note type="userid" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">footcite:Burroughs72</note></biblStruct></biblio></raweb>